<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>BiteofanApple by Brian Schrader</title><link>http://brianschrader.com</link><description>Thoughts, and ramblings about technology, programming, history, and whatever else I'm interested in.</description><lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2018 00:02:45 +0000</lastBuildDate><category>programming</category><category>history</category><category>science</category><category>personal</category><category>technology</category><generator>PyRSS2Gen-1.1.0</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><image><url>http://www.gravatar.com/avatar/11b074a636e00292c98e3e60f7e16595</url><title>sonicrocketman</title><link>http://brianschrader.com</link></image><item><title>Blogging has an Image Problem</title><link>http://brianschrader.com/archive/blogging-has-an-image-problem/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I've asked a few people recently about the differences between services like Facebook, Twitter, Instagram and traditional blogs. The answers are almost entirely conventional not technical, and this leads me to what I think is a big reason why blogging has receded in recent years: blogging has an image problem. It's supposed to be for everyone, but lots of people, who are sometimes extremely active on social media sites, are hesitant to start a blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a technical standpoint, the combination of a blog (that supports WebMentions and/or ActivityPub) and a good Feed Reader can provide nearly all of the features people require from a modern social network (a combination that &lt;a href="https://pine.blog/"&gt;Pine.blog&lt;/a&gt; aims to provide). The technology exists, but to get started with blogging is still too complex. On Facebook or Twitter you can sign up and be posting in minutes, you can easily find other things to follow, and you can easily see what others are saying. Typical Feed Readers solve only one of these problems. You can follow other sites, but you can't post to your own, and you can't easily discover new sites to follow. Having a blog then means that you have to switch from reading a post in one app, to posting to your own blog in another, which makes blogging feel arcane and clunky. And even with both a good reader and a blog, it's still fairly difficult to find interesting things to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://pine.blog/"&gt;Pine.blog&lt;/a&gt; is my attempt to solve all three of these issues at once and make reading blogs and blogging on your own site just as easy as browsing your timeline and posting to Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>blogging</category><category> open web</category><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/blogging-has-an-image-problem</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2018 00:02:00 -0800</pubDate></item><item><title>Feed Readers and Local News</title><link>http://brianschrader.com/archive/feed-readers-and-local-news/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Interest in local news outlets has been declining over time. Bigger, flashier news outlets with more resources can attract more users and more traffic. But local news provides so much valuable information to the people living in the communities they serve and arguably this news generally effects reader's lives more than national news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been thinking a lot lately about how &lt;a href="https://pine.blog/"&gt;Pine.blog&lt;/a&gt; can help promote local news. Adding individual sections for each "locale" is obviously untenable since the Pine.blog directory is manually curated, but simply tagging a site as a "reputable local news outlet" might be enough. The issue then is deciding what  reputable", "local", and "news outlet" mean from the outside.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>pine.blog</category><category> local news</category><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/feed-readers-and-local-news</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Oct 2018 18:58:00 -0800</pubDate></item><item><title>Pine.blog 1.2 is Out!</title><link>http://brianschrader.com/archive/pineblog-12-is-out/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The wait is over: &lt;a href="https://pine.blog/"&gt;Pine.blog&lt;/a&gt; v1.2 is out! This update has been steeping for a while now, and I hope you all like it. Along with a ton of iOS features (listed below), I've also given the site a makeover, added a demo video, added a 7-day free trial for new users, included a lot more info about how Pine.blog works and how to use it, as well as quite a few little web UI enhancements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;New Features&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New Discover/Search tab allows you to find and follow new people and sites directly from the app!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New Profile tab shows you which sites/people you've recommended and which ones you follow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search for any site in the Pine Directory right from the app.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post to your own site from the app!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow and Unfollow Sites directly from the app.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow sites using a URL from the app!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In-App Notifications now give you more feedback about what's going on in the app.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Added a way to report bugs right from the app (RIP inbox).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Enhancements&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Images are front and center now&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can now browse your entire favorites history.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scrolling the timeline is much smoother&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adds Haptic Feedback to lots of buttons for a more responsive feeling interface&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fonts are crisper, cleaner, and more readable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Fixes&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fixes a bug where the app could crash in the background which would stop it from preloading new items&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fixes a bug with the Done button and swipe gesture in the article web view&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lots of other minor fixes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're using Pine.blog and like it, please tell your friends, and if you've never heard of it, &lt;a href="https://pine.blog/"&gt;check it out! &amp;#8594;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>pine.blog</category><category> version release</category><category> 1.2</category><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/pineblog-12-is-out</guid><pubDate>Wed, 17 Oct 2018 05:10:00 -0800</pubDate></item><item><title>The Scope Creep is Real</title><link>http://brianschrader.com/archive/the-scope-creep-is-real/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;With development on &lt;a href="https://pine.blog"&gt;Pine.blog&lt;/a&gt; v1.2 wrapping up, and a releasable version in sight, I've been thinking about why this version has taken so much longer than the previous two. My answer in short: I kept adding features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pine.blog 1.2 is a huge update, and it was intended to be, but as time went on it kept getting bigger mostly because I kept wanting "just one more feature". On the web side, I've improved the performance, finished most of the groundwork for the public API, added lots of tests to ensure I'm not accidentally breaking things, and added a 7-day free trial for new users. On the iOS side I've added the ability to follow and unfollow sites directly from the app, recommend sites to other users, browse a site's previous posts, you can now post to your own site, and there's a new Search/Discover tab with a browsable directory of new and interesting sites to follow. All in all, version 1.2 has probably 2-3 times as many features as the 1.1 version does, and I can say that v1.2 is at a point now where it has most of the features I originally envisioned for Pine.blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all that though, I'm not sure if it's a better strategy to release a steady stream of minor updates or hold things back for a few big releases every couple months. The same work gets done, but the steady stream means that more features would be released sooner instead of being held back for a major release. On the flip side though, its a lot harder to promote and get people excited about a minor release than a major one. And even if one approach is better than the other, I'll probably still find myself tacking on "just one more thing" into every release (I guess the hard part is limiting myself to just one "just one more thing").&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, I'm super excited to get v1.2 out into the world, so keep a weather eye on the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>pine</category><category> development</category><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/the-scope-creep-is-real</guid><pubDate>Sat, 06 Oct 2018 20:34:00 -0800</pubDate></item><item><title>Pine v1.1 is Out &amp;amp; A Special Moment</title><link>http://brianschrader.com/archive/pine-v11-is-out-amp-a-special-moment/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Pine &lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/pine-blog/id1401683628?ls=1&amp;amp;mt=8"&gt;v1.1 for iOS&lt;/a&gt; is out today! This release ended up being a bit smaller than I'd originally intended, but it has enough fixes and improvements that I didn't want to sit on it any longer. Along with a few bug fixes and performance enhancements, Version 1.1 adds a couple of really cool features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Images now show up in a beautiful slideshow in the timeline, rather than just in the full post view.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Siri can now read the contents of an article to you, which is really nice for keeping up with the news on a walk or ride.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If a feed doesn't specify an image, Pine will grab the site's App Icon, or Favicon to show instead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fixes a nasty issue that would cause scrolling to be really choppy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sign up for a &lt;a href="https://pine.blog"&gt;Pine.blog&lt;/a&gt; subscription to start using the app today!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Pine Joins the Wall of Apps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On an episode of &lt;a href="http://atp.fm"&gt;ATP&lt;/a&gt; years back, Marco Arment mentioned that he gets prints of his app icons made in order to have a physical reminder of what he's built. I really liked this idea, so for the last couple of years I've done the same thing, and last week, my &lt;a href="https://fractureme.com"&gt;Fracture&lt;/a&gt; of the Pine iOS app icon arrived and is now on my wall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img
    class="image-center"
    style="max-width:25em;"
    src="/images/blog/pine-counter.jpg"
    alt=""
/&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;caption&gt;
    I think this is my favorite print so far. The colors are stunning.
&lt;/caption&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To paraphrase Marco: Software Developers spend hundreds of hours building a thing that can affect hundreds (or thousands) of people, but since it's software, you can't touch it or take a picture of you in front of it like you can with a bridge or something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img
    class="image-center"
    style="max-width:30em;"
    src="/images/blog/fractures.jpg"
    alt=""
/&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;caption&gt;
    Pine joins Adventurer's Codex and MyGeneRank as the third app I've built (or had a big hand in building).
&lt;/caption&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you build and ship software, there's no tacky trophy, no photo of the ribbon cutting, or blueprints of the structure; nothing you can easily take home and keep as a reminder. Having physical prints (and especially Fracture prints) of your app icons is a nice little momento of all of the effort and time you spent to make a thing.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>indie</category><category> app development</category><category> fracture</category><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/pine-v11-is-out-amp-a-special-moment</guid><pubDate>Fri, 13 Jul 2018 18:33:00 -0800</pubDate></item><item><title>On the Future of Social Media</title><link>http://brianschrader.com/archive/on-the-future-of-social-media/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I just finished the newest episode of the &lt;a href="https://www.vox.com/ezra-klein-show-podcast"&gt;Ezra Klein Show&lt;/a&gt; with Jaron Lanier. Jaron spends a good portion of the episode talking about how the systems we've built into the internet, and social media specifically, have really had a negative effect on civil discourse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://overcast.fm/+F_9G-Gkus/1:01:37"&gt;One question Ezra brought up&lt;/a&gt; really struck me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you were building, or you were redesigning a social network that would call forth our better selves... what do you think would be the parameters of that? What rules would you set such that it would urge us to be a better version of ourselves, not a worse version?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their discussion really resonated with me. Jaron mentioned that he thinks that the algorithmic nature of today's social media and the algorithms used in advertising are both large causes of a lot of the strife we see online. He argues &lt;a href="https://overcast.fm/+F_9G-Gkus/30:58"&gt;that how we measure engagement&lt;/a&gt; (clicks, posts, activity, etc) allows  the most impassioned people (and often the most hateful) to drive the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been thinking a lot about what makes good social media recently because of &lt;a href="https://pine.blog"&gt;Pine&lt;/a&gt;. I think that a new generation of social media will revolve around the principles that users have control over what they see, that they own the content they post, and that no one person or company controls all the ways they see the world. I think that, combined, these changes make social media better for us all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a really good episode; highly recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://overcast.fm/+F_9G-Gkus"&gt;Jaron Lanier&#8217;s case for deleting social media right now &amp;#8594;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>social media</category><category> algorithms</category><category> development</category><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/on-the-future-of-social-media</guid><pubDate>Wed, 11 Jul 2018 01:40:00 -0800</pubDate></item><item><title>RSS Has Already Won</title><link>http://brianschrader.com/archive/rss-has-already-won/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It's been a little over &lt;a href="https://www.theverge.com/2013/3/13/4101144/google-shuts-down-reader-rss-aggregation-service"&gt;5 years since Google Reader shut down&lt;/a&gt; and the world of RSS readers was tossed into the junk drawer of collective memory. But, looking back on it today, I'd actually argue that RSS and Feeds as a whole never really disappeared, only the Feed Readers did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In building &lt;a href="https://pine.blog"&gt;Pine&lt;/a&gt;, and as a long time Feed Reader user, I've been pleasantly surprised over these last 5 years to see that most sites still have RSS feeds. Sure, Facebook and Twitter don't support them, but YouTube, Reddit, Squarespace, Wordpress and so many more do by default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feeds of all kinds still exist, nearly forgotten, in the markup of most websites, and this means that Feed Readers can, and will, make a comeback someday. The foundations are already laid; the hard work is done. RSS Feeds became a standard, and were built into the tools we use to make the web today. It's almost as if we laid the tracks and built the trains for a trans-continental railroad, but we've just forgotten how to sell tickets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we're waiting for now is a resurgence and a new interpretation of what a Feed Reader can or should be. Sites like &lt;a href="https://micro.blog"&gt;Micro.blog&lt;/a&gt; focus heavily on building a social network of readers and microbloggers, while &lt;a href="https://pine.blog"&gt;Pine&lt;/a&gt; focuses on discovering new and exciting people and sites to follow and new ways to interact with them, and &lt;a href="http://rivernewsapp.com"&gt;RiverNews&lt;/a&gt; is a more traditional reader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Others have said this, but I think it's more true by the day: the Feed Readers, they're coming back.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>pine</category><category> rss</category><category> standards</category><category> open web</category><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/rss-has-already-won</guid><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jul 2018 23:39:00 -0800</pubDate></item><item><title>Pine for iOS Released!</title><link>http://brianschrader.com/archive/pine-for-ios-released/</link><description>&lt;div class="image-container"&gt;
&lt;img
    src="/images/blog/pine/pine-app-logo-light.png"
    alt="Pine.blog iOS App Logo"
    style="max-width:150px; width:80%; box-shadow:3px 3px 5px darkgrey; border-radius:30px; padding:0; margin-right:10px; float:right;"
/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's official: the &lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/pine-blog/id1401683628?ls=1&amp;amp;mt=8"&gt;Pine.blog app for iOS&lt;/a&gt; is available on the App Store! The app is free for all and requires a premium subscription to &lt;a href="https://pine.blog"&gt;Pine.blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this version you can quickly and easily check up on your timeline and your favorites, and the app refreshes in the background so that you're always up to date with the latest news and posts from any site you follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Version 1.0 is pretty slimmed down, which is why I was able to get something out so quickly after the initial Pine launch, but don't worry; there's lots of great features planned for the app. Overall, I'm trying to keep releases fairly small so that they can be released more often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, I'm planning for v1.1 to include the ability to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post to your own site, just like you can on the website.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;See who you follow and to follow and unfollow sites from the app.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preview images from posts directly from the timeline (like how a lot of Twitter apps show images).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to all the Pine users for making this possible, and if you enjoy Pine, please tell your friends!&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>pine</category><category> ios</category><category> app</category><category> release</category><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/pine-for-ios-released</guid><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jul 2018 23:32:00 -0800</pubDate></item><item><title>A Sneak Peek: Pine for iOS</title><link>http://brianschrader.com/archive/a-sneak-peek-pine-for-ios/</link><description>&lt;style&gt;
    div.image-container {
        width: unset;
        text-align:center;
        padding: 0px;
        float:none;
    }
    div img.pine-screenshot {
        max-height: unset;
        max-width: unset;
    }
    img.pine-screenshot {
        box-shadow: 4px 4px 5px #ccc;
        padding: 0;
        margin-right: 15px;
        display: inline;
        height:350pt;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's been a few busy weeks since I first &lt;a href="//pine.blog"&gt;launched Pine&lt;/a&gt;, a new kind of Feed Reader. And while it's not quite ready for prime-time yet, here's a sneak peek at the official Pine app for iOS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The app will be free and require a Pine subscription&lt;/strong&gt; to use. My favorite features though are the &lt;strong&gt;Dark Mode&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Dark App Icon&lt;/strong&gt; support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first version of the app is pretty bare bones with only only a few screens: your timeline, likes listing, and full article view. And while you'll of course be able to share and like posts, Version 1.0 will not have any sort of search or follow/unfollow support (though that's coming soon afterwards).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="image-container"&gt;
&lt;img
    class="pine-screenshot"
    src="/images/blog/pine/820-likes-dark.PNG"
/&gt;
&lt;img
    class="pine-screenshot"
    src="/images/blog/pine/820-post-light.PNG"
/&gt;
&lt;img
    class="pine-screenshot"
    src="/images/blog/pine/820-post-dark.PNG"
/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deciding what to cut and what to keep is always hard, but I've once you've set up Pine in the browser, this version of the app should have enough features for a nice day-to-day experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been using the app for a couple of days now and it's really shaping up into something special. Hopefully it will be ready for launch soon.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>pine</category><category> ios</category><category> app</category><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/a-sneak-peek-pine-for-ios</guid><pubDate>Fri, 15 Jun 2018 12:42:00 -0800</pubDate></item><item><title>Announcing Pine: Microblogging for a New Generation &#127881;</title><link>http://brianschrader.com/archive/announcing-pine-microblogging-for-a-new-generation-/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img
    alt="Pine Logo"
    class="image-right"
    style="max-width:200px;"
    src="https://pine.blog/static/images/pine-logo-color-500.png"
/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I'm announcing &lt;a href="https://pine.blog"&gt;Pine, a new kind of RSS Reader and Microblogging client&lt;/a&gt;. I've been developing Pine, in addition to a bunch of other projects for a while now, and it's finally time to show it off to the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a classical sense, Pine is a Feed Reader, but it's really more of a successor to my old &lt;a href="/archive/microblogger-status-updates-and-more/"&gt;Microblogger project&lt;/a&gt; from way back. Not only can users follow the people and sites they want, but you can also use Pine to post to your own Wordpress site and find new sites and people using the built in search. In a lot of ways Pine and &lt;a href="https://micro.blog"&gt;Micro.blog&lt;/a&gt; are similar with a few key differences and, from what I can tell, both Manton and I started working on them at around the same time. Pine is my contribution to a new ecosystem of open social networking tools and services. Anyone on Micro.blog can follow people on Pine and vice-versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pine is also my first venture into building paid software. It's $5 per month and at that price I don't have to sell ads or do anything shady to earn money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been reluctant to post anything about Pine until it officially launched, but now that it has, I've got a few interesting design decisions I'd like to talk about. Building a feed reader has always been on my to-do list, and it turns out that there's a lot more to it than just parsing feeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've got a lot of great new features planned, including an iOS app which should be coming soon. If you're interested, give Pine a shot, and let me know what you think!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://pine.blog"&gt;Pine &amp;#8594;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>pine</category><category> software</category><category> announcement</category><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/announcing-pine-microblogging-for-a-new-generation-</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 11:30:00 -0800</pubDate></item></channel></rss>