<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>BiteofanApple by Brian Schrader</title><link>http://brianschrader.com</link><description>Thoughts, and ramblings about technology, programming, history, and whatever else I'm interested in.</description><lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Jul 2017 20:12:45 +0000</lastBuildDate><category>programming</category><category>history</category><category>science</category><category>personal</category><category>technology</category><generator>PyRSS2Gen-1.1.0</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><image><url>http://www.gravatar.com/avatar/11b074a636e00292c98e3e60f7e16595</url><title>sonicrocketman</title><link>http://brianschrader.com</link></image><item><title>Adventurer's Codex: XMPP</title><link>http://brianschrader.com/archive/adventurers-codex-xmpp/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;You might have noticed in my &lt;a href="/archive/adventurers-codex-the-stack/"&gt;last post in this series&lt;/a&gt; that I mentioned Adventurer's Codex using &lt;a href="http://ejabberd.im"&gt;Ejabberd&lt;/a&gt;. A few of you might even be a little abhorred by the idea that a modern piece of software has even a line of XML running through it, but it's true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;But it's XML!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;XMPP is an old standard these days, and I think it's safe to say that it's earned a reputation for being a very complex and stateful XML-based protocol. But XMPP has also had years of industry giants testing its limits and adding new and improved functionality to the spec. All of that means that the XMPP spec has tons of recommendations and countless extensions which can make it difficult to approach as a newbie, but it also means that nearly anything you need to do with XMPP has already been done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In building &lt;a href="https://adventurerscodex.com"&gt;Adventurer's Codex&lt;/a&gt; we wanted to leverage as many server technologies as possible with as little custom logic as we could manage. Nobody on the team wanted to write chat or pubsub functionality, or handle scaling the system with multiple nodes, and we wanted the system to be built on open technologies that support the idea of a standards based Open Web and all of the inter-compatibility that such a web entails. We looked around, and here was this perfectly good, time-tested standard just lying there, waiting for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://ejabberd.im"&gt;Ejabberd&lt;/a&gt; has lots of great resources and chat rooms out there filled with people that can help you and the majority of commonly used specs like &lt;a href="https://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0045.html"&gt;Multi-User Chat&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0060.html"&gt;PubSub&lt;/a&gt; are very well documented. The server software is robust and adaptable, and the defaults are already pretty good at getting you up and running. Perhaps most importantly, the client-side support for XMPP is really good: The web has &lt;a href="http://strophe.im"&gt;Strophe.js&lt;/a&gt; and all of the native platforms have either built in support or a wealth of Open Source options for speaking XMPP, so expanding support is easy. All of these things came together to make XMPP a worthwhile choice for our needs... even if it's XML.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>adventurerscodex</category><category> dnd</category><category> software</category><category> xmpp</category><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/adventurers-codex-xmpp</guid><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jul 2017 13:12:00 -0800</pubDate></item><item><title>Adventurer's Codex: The Stack</title><link>http://brianschrader.com/archive/adventurers-codex-the-stack/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I figure that if I'm going to write a series of posts about how and why &lt;a href="https://adventurerscodex.com"&gt;Adventurer's Codex&lt;/a&gt; works the way it does, it might be good to first talk about what's actually powering it. It's time to talk about our "stack".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People like to think that a project's internal technologies are chosen by seasoned professionals who carefully weighed the differences between competing options over the course of months, but from what I've seen it's usually just whatever the first developers on the project liked or already knew how to use and &lt;a href="https://adventurerscodex.com"&gt;Adventurer's Codex&lt;/a&gt; is no different. Before we started we asked around for suggestions on frameworks to use, and when in doubt we used what we'd learned at work. We were not seasoned architects and we didn't spend months deciding, we were (are) anxious developers trying to bring our dream to life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Stack&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the client-side, we went with &lt;a href="http://knockoutjs.com"&gt;KnockoutJS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; and a ton of additional libraries. The trouble with the front-end world is that you essentially have to build up your own OS in the browser. Need notifications, persistence, url parsing, OAuth compatibility, or master-detail view hierarchies? Either you find one, or you build one. In our case, we built a lot. Why we chose to build out so many of our own custom libraries is a story for another time, but we do try to use existing libraries, like &lt;a href="https://github.com/millermedeiros/js-signals"&gt;Signals.js&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://strophe.im"&gt;Strophe.js&lt;/a&gt;, and more as often as we can. But when it came to a few crucial things like Persistence and MVC structure, we went our own way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The server-side came a lot later in the timeline&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, and collectively we have far more experience with the kinds of tech involved. We took the Marco Arment strategy: use the most boring, proven software you can find. We went with &lt;a href="http://www.django-rest-framework.org"&gt;Django REST&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://gunicorn-docs.readthedocs.io/en/stable/"&gt;Gunicorn&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/jwilder/nginx-proxy"&gt;Nginx&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.postgresql.org"&gt;Postgres&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://ejabberd.im"&gt;Ejabberd&lt;/a&gt;, all  inside of &lt;a href="https://www.docker.com"&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt;, on &lt;a href="https://www.centos.org"&gt;CentOS&lt;/a&gt;, on &lt;a href="https://www.linode.com"&gt;Linode&lt;/a&gt;. Nothing exciting there (except arguably Django REST) which is good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, if I could go back in time, there's a &lt;a href="http://knockoutjs.com"&gt;few things I'd change about our client-side tech stack&lt;/a&gt;, but knowing what we did back then, I think we made decent choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/archive/adventurers-codex-behind-the-curtain/"&gt;Part 1: Behind the Curtain &amp;#8594;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;1.&lt;/sup&gt; Don't email me. I know "Knockout is Dead". &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;2.&lt;/sup&gt; Until version 1.4, we could get away with hosting on GitHub pages because we had no backend. The app, including it's datastorage, was (and is at time of writing) all done in-browser. More on that in another post.
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>adventurerscodex</category><category> dnd</category><category> software</category><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/adventurers-codex-the-stack</guid><pubDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2017 17:28:00 -0800</pubDate></item><item><title>Measuring Sticks</title><link>http://brianschrader.com/archive/measuring-sticks/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Humans have a notoriously bad grasp of large numbers. We can see that 10 is 9 more than 1 and we have some feeling as to just how much "9 more" really is, but  the difference between 100 and 200 isn't as easy to gauge, let alone 1,000,000 and 1,000,000,000. When I'm dealing with these kinds of huge numbers, I try to boil it down to a simple comparison between things I already know: an iPhone is worth almost 5 months of groceries for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same approach helps when dealing with historical timelines. &lt;a href="http://waitbutwhy.com/2016/01/horizontal-history.html"&gt;WaitButWhy did something similar a while back&lt;/a&gt; by using generations of people to measure history. For things on a broader timescale, I've started using a few different metrics. For example, Issac Newton died roughly before the founding of the United States&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;. In fact, if we use the United State's age as a measuring stick, it leads to some interesting comparisons (because it's me, all of the comparisons are going to be to Roman history):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Fall of the Byzantine Empire&lt;/strong&gt; was (roughly) &lt;strong&gt;twice as long ago&lt;/strong&gt; as the founding of the United States is to today.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Fall of the Western Roman Empire&lt;/strong&gt; was over &lt;strong&gt;six times as long ago&lt;/strong&gt; as the founding of the U.S.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means that as ancient as we think the Byzantine Empire is today, we're twice as close to them, as they are to the fall of their western half! It's crazy, but using this method we can also compare historical time periods, and this is the meat of what I'm getting at with all this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, I've been reading &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/SPQR-History-Ancient-Mary-Beard/dp/0871404230"&gt;Mary Beard's fantastic book, SPQR&lt;/a&gt;, and even though I've been down the rabbit hole of Roman History over four other times&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; I keep finding new fascinating things, and the biggest one is always the sheer scale of the timelines involved. We never really stop to think about just how long the "ancient" world was around compared to our "modern" one. To keep this short, here's an example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The founding of the city of Rome is, mythically, 753 BCE, and the toppling of the kings and the establishment of the republic was in 509 BCE. Using our measuring stick from before means that the age of the legendary 7 Kings of Rome was roughly the same as the age of the current United States, and that &lt;strong&gt;the Roman Republic (509 BCE-27 BCE) was, somewhat conveniently, exactly twice as old as the United States is today&lt;/strong&gt;. For completeness, the Empire lasted a bit longer but was also about double the U.S.'s current age (by traditional dating of the fall of the west). All of that comes together to mean that the Roman state, from fiery birth to limping death, lasted &lt;strong&gt;five to nine times longer than the United States&lt;/strong&gt; has been around, depending on which ending date you use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with all that context, what's really crazy is that the height of ancient Egyptian civilization was over 14 times as long ago as the founding of the United States, or about 2.3 times as long ago as the founding of the Roman Republic. We've all seen that meme that Cleopatra was born closer to the current day than the building of the Pyramids at Giza, but it's also impressive to see just how much closer to us she really is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our popular retelling of the founding of the United States is already starting to become somewhat of a mythical folktale and the founding of Rome is shrouded in unsolvable mystery, so I can only imagine the kinds of stories the Romans told each other about the foundings of the even more ancient to them Egyptians, or near prehistoric kingdoms of Mesopotamia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;1.&lt;/sup&gt; Yes, I know there's 50 years missing in there, but go with it.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;2.&lt;/sup&gt; My Roman history tours in chronological order: The History of Rome podcast, The History of Rome by Livy, The History of Byzantium podcast, and full re-listening of the History of Rome.
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>history</category><category> roman</category><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/measuring-sticks</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2017 10:37:00 -0800</pubDate></item><item><title>Adventurer's Codex: Behind the Curtain</title><link>http://brianschrader.com/archive/adventurers-codex-behind-the-curtain/</link><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our tale starts as many such tales often do. It was the end of July in the year two-thousand and fifteen by western reckoning and three friends met in a busy tavern in a sleepy neighborhood in San Diego. Their quest: to change the way Dungeons and Dragons would be played forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost two years ago, I started a project with a few friends that last year we turned into a full-on company: &lt;a href="//adventurerscodex.com/"&gt;Adventurer's Codex&lt;/a&gt;. For no particular reason, I've never spoken about the project here, but I'm going to change that, if nothing but for posterity. Originally I wanted to write a single "What I've learned while building Adventurer's Codex" post, but it got too big and covered so many unrelated topics that I'm just going to have to make it into a series of smaller posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Codex, But For Adventurers!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who don't know: Adventurer's Codex is a web-based toolset for playing 5th Edition Dungeons and Dragons (D&amp;amp;D 5e). It has a number of features for both players and DMs (Dungeon Masters, aka Game Masters) with a focus on real-time, collaborative play. I've played D&amp;amp;D for years, and so have the other two founders, and we all think that while the classic pen-and-paper version of D&amp;amp;D is great, there are some definite improvements to be made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're interested in &lt;a href="//adventurerscodex.com/"&gt;seeing what Adventurer's Codex can do, checkout the site and try it out&lt;/a&gt;, and if you don't know what D&amp;amp;D is, or you've never played, then I strongly encourage you to try it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;No Choice but to Rise to the Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Software design has always been interesting to me. I've spent countless hours learning about just how lots of mature projects, like CPython, Cocoa, and iOS, work at the high level, and how their designs limit or enhance their core features. So when it came down to designing Adventurer's Codex, I jumped at the chance. The only trouble was: I'd never actually designed anything so big before; none of us had. And so, like with many projects, the architecture for Adventurer's Codex grew as we did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we started, I had no idea how to professionally set up servers, design modern APIs, or design multi-tier web applications. I had this website, which I was proud of, and in-and-out of my day job I'd built lots of different types of web and native software. Coming from iOS/Cocoa and Java/Spring development at the time meant that I was always accustomed to having a very large, opinionated framework to guide the design of whatever I was building, but when it comes to front-end Javascript, that's just not the case. In the browser, we were forced/free to pick and choose our own tools, libraries, and conventions and because of this, we stumbled a lot in the early days: tearing through three different data storage strategies and three more major code architecture changes. Every one of these experiences taught us something about software design, but it also slowed us down, and nearly burnt me out, but all of that is (hopefully) behind us now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although getting this far has been a huge undertaking, because of the way we chose to develop Adventurer's Codex, we've been able to slowly roll out bits and pieces of infrastructure over almost a year while still having a working product. If I had to give advice for anyone in the same position: ask people who've done it before. A few invaluable people at my local programming meetup group had experience with all of the things I didn't and were more than happy to point me in the right direction. The internet is great, but it's actually pretty difficult to find out how to design modern web systems from scratch with just a vague notion and Google.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TL;DR: Turns out, designing, architecting, and managing complex software is hard...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
* Woo, broke the streak!
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>adventurer's codex</category><category> development</category><category> dnd</category><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/adventurers-codex-behind-the-curtain</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 21:52:00 -0800</pubDate></item><item><title>The Cloudbleed Bug: An Overview</title><link>http://brianschrader.com/archive/the-cloudbleed-bug-an-overview/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bugs.chromium.org/p/project-zero/issues/detail?id=1139"&gt;Tavis Ormandy (Chromium Bug Tracker) &amp;#8594;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It became clear after a while we were looking at chunks of uninitialized memory interspersed with valid data. The program that this uninitialized data was coming from just happened to have the data I wanted in memory at the time...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A while later, we figured out how to reproduce the problem. It looked like that if an html page hosted behind cloudflare had a specific combination of unbalanced tags, the proxy would intersperse pages of uninitialized memory into the output...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We fetched a few live samples, and we observed encryption keys, cookies, passwords, chunks of POST data and even HTTPS requests for other major cloudflare-hosted sites from other users. Once we understood what we were seeing and the implications, we immediately stopped and contacted cloudflare security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A tweet you never want to see." src="/images/blog/the-tweet-to-end-it-all.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never a tweet you want to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=13718810"&gt;tptacek (Hacker News) &amp;#8594;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crazy thing here is that the Project Zero people were joking last night about a disclosure that was going to keep everyone at work late today. And, this morning, Google announced the SHA-1 collision, which everyone (including the insiders who leaked that the SHA-1 collision was coming) thought was the big announcement.
Nope. A SHA-1 collision, it turns out, is the minor security news of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/incident-report-on-memory-leak-caused-by-cloudflare-parser-bug/"&gt;Cloudflare Blog &amp;#8594;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bug was serious because the leaked memory could contain private information and because it had been cached by search engines. We have also not discovered any evidence of malicious exploits of the bug or other reports of its existence...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are grateful that it was found by one of the world&#8217;s top security research teams and reported to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This broke late last night PST, and while Travis Ormandy and the hardworking team at Cloudflare have resolved the situation, the consequences of this bug are not small. Cloudflare is a very large CDN that sits in front of tens of thousands of sites and all of them are potentially affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="My report" src="/images/blog/ac-cloudbleed-report.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/pirate/sites-using-cloudflare/blob/master/README.md"&gt;List of sites affected by Cloudbleed &amp;#8594;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>security</category><category> ssl</category><category> encryption</category><category> heartbleed</category><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/the-cloudbleed-bug-an-overview</guid><pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2017 11:06:00 -0800</pubDate></item><item><title>Comments with Cited References</title><link>http://brianschrader.com/archive/comments-with-cited-references/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A while back I got into the habit of adding links to any source code that I copy from the web. It's a small addition but it's helped me a lot when I need to go back and fix bugs long after I've forgotten what I did or why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class="swift"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;
// From: http://bit.ly/2ltsDF6
extension Data {
    /// Create hexadecimal string representation of &lt;code&gt;Data&lt;/code&gt; object.
    ///
    /// - returns: &lt;code&gt;String&lt;/code&gt; representation of this &lt;code&gt;Data&lt;/code&gt; object.
    func hexadecimal() -&amp;gt; String {
        return map { String(format: "%02x", $0) }
            .joined(separator: "")
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This technique is also really useful if you encounter unsupported or buggy behavior in some framework or library and you write a weird workaround or unconventional solution. In those cases I don't just document that it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a workaround, I try to link to a place that explains or tracks the bug (like the GitHub Issue or Stack Overflow page).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class="swift"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;
switch identifier {
case "SpecialWaitStep", "OtherSpecialWaitStep":
    // Wait steps aren't backward navigable.
    // https://github.com/ResearchKit/ResearchKit/issues/914
    return nil
default:
    return getStep("...")
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way if anyone (future me included) needs to go back to fix that section of code, they'll at least know why that hack is there.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;1.&lt;/sup&gt; Hell, maybe by then the issue has been solved and they can even remove your hacky code.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!-- Begin Syntax Stylesheet --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;link rel="stylesheet" href="/bin/highlight.default.min.css"&gt;
&lt;script src="/bin/highlight.min.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script&gt;hljs.initHighlightingOnLoad();&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>code</category><category> links</category><category></category><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/comments-with-cited-references</guid><pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2017 12:29:00 -0800</pubDate></item><item><title>So Many Words Written, So Many More to Come</title><link>http://brianschrader.com/archive/so-many-words-written-so-many-more-to-come/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Apparently I'm 236 words short of 50,000 total words written for my blog over 161 posts&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;. That's about 309 words per post on average. I was playing around with the site just now and just out of curiosity I ran this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ find archive/ -name "*.md"|xargs -I {} cat {} | wc -w
   49764
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now curious, I did some more digging to see what I could learn; here's a few different statistics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Longest post:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/archive/a-vision-of-the-open-web/"&gt;A Vision of the Open Web&lt;/a&gt; - 1574 words&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shortest post:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/archive/bloodmoon-eclipse/"&gt;BloodMoon Eclipse Photos&lt;/a&gt; - 6 words&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most average length post:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/archive/can-we-save-the-open-web/"&gt;Can we save the open web?&lt;/a&gt; - 309 words&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we count all the drafts I've never published (but still have) the grand total goes up to 64,088 words.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That's 14,324 words unpublished.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;154 different tags used on posts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most used tags:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blog: 21 times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;web: 14 times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;space: 10 times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;open web: 10 times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blogging: 10 times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;python: 8 times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Least used tags:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;D&amp;amp;D, FCC, OS X, alternatives, angular... (and 105 more)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just for the occasion, I made up a pretty graph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A graph of word count." src="/images/blog/post-word-count-50k-words.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's hard to believe that I've been blogging for almost 5 years on this site, and if you count my two blogs before this one, then it's been almost 6 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in case you're wondering: yes, this post is just over 236 words. &#127881;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; Technically that 50,000 word count includes handcrafted HTML inside a post's markdown. It's not &lt;i&gt;that much&lt;/i&gt; of a factor and I'm defending my claim because technically I wrote that HTML so there.
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>blog</category><category> stats</category><category> metablogging</category><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/so-many-words-written-so-many-more-to-come</guid><pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 19:58:00 -0800</pubDate></item><item><title>An Ode to the 13 Inch MacBook Pro</title><link>http://brianschrader.com/archive/an-ode-to-the-13-inch-macbook-pro/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I got my first Mac in 2010: A &lt;a href="https://support.apple.com/kb/SP583?locale=en_US"&gt;base model 13" Macbook Pro&lt;/a&gt;. Like lots of people I got it in my first year of college with Apple's Education Discount. I had it all the way through college until 2015 when I got my current &lt;a href="https://support.apple.com/kb/SP715?locale=en_US"&gt;13" Retina Macbook Pro&lt;/a&gt;. In that time, I'd dropped it, fixed it, swapped out the spinning platter for an SSD, added RAM, and made it my own. I learned to program on it, I played PC games with it, and &lt;a href="/archive/writing-for-a-website-you-built-from-scratch/"&gt;I built this website with it&lt;/a&gt;. I used every ounce of power that 2.4GHz Core2-Duo could spare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short: I loved that machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That Macbook Pro turned me into a Mac person. I justified buying it by saying that I'd build iPhone apps with it, but that never really came to pass. I did learn about Unix and Bash though, and that knowledge changed how I used computers forever. Back then I looked forward to 2 things every year: the new iPhone OS announcement and the Mac OS X announcement. I even took time off work one year to stay home and watch WWDC talks in a time before I'd ever worked on iOS apps professionally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short: I found what I wanted to do because of that Mac and it changed me forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="My mac at a donut-shop in portland" src="/images/blog/doughnuts-and-chai.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2015 I got my current Mac. When I passed on my old 2010 MBP it was dented, missing a foot, and had no CD drive (I took it out to save weight and then lost it). Fresh out of college I forked over literally all of the money I had for a specced out 13" rMBP. Two and a half years later I can say, it's the best computer I've ever owned or used. I've taken it everywhere, and it's risen to every challenge I've thrown at it (except modern PC gaming but I don't play a lot anyway).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Excluding a few months when I experimented with building PCs in college&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; and at my old day-job, my Macs have always been my primary and only machines, and now my 2015 rMBP is my work machine too. They've both been as flexible, durable, extensible, and powerful as I could ask.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Part About Apple Nowadays&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That long preamble was more than a nice stroll down memory lane. I may not have the pedigree of &lt;a href="http://hypercritical.co"&gt;some mac users&lt;/a&gt; but I love the Mac and over the years I've seen Apple seem to forget how much people love, use, and need the Mac to do what they do, and it makes me sad. Maybe they're working on something awesome for the Mac and I hope if they are that it's as great as it can be, but it doesn't look that way from the outside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could stand here and say that I wish the 13" MacBook Pro had dedicated graphics card and quad-core CPU options (and I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; do wish that), but after 7 years I just don't see that happening. I guess what I want is something to prove that the Mac is still worth something to Apple. The Mac community is strong enough to last for years without Apple updating much, but that's not something I look forward to, it's a last resort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Circle Be Unbroken&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Growing up, my mom had (and still has) a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PowerBook_G4"&gt;17" Titanium Powerbook G4&lt;/a&gt;, and she used it for almost 10 years, she was the first Mac user in the house, and though I used them in middle and high school I'd always had a Windows PC at home. In 2009 a coworker and long-time Mac user convinced my parents to get me an iPhone, and a few months later I bought my first Mac.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since that time I've convinced my sister, several coworkers, friends, and many complete strangers to get Macs. I've always said the price was worth it, and even though I think that's less true now, I'd still recommend the Mac over the alternative. All of those people are using Macs today because some enthusiastic college student convinced them to get one, and he got his Mac and iPhone because of a passionate Mac user who convinced him back in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That old MacBook is till alive; it's my mom's laptop now. It's worked well for her until this year: she got a GoPro and needs to edit the video. That MacBook can do a lot of things, but rendering 1080p and 4K video comfortably isn't one of them. If and when she gets a new computer, I'll probably ask for that MacBook back. There's not much I can use it for, but just like my old iPhones, it'll be a nice thing to keep around for the memories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;1.&lt;/sup&gt; I also experimented with Linux in college, but that went from recreational use to professional use.
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>apple</category><category> macbook pro</category><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/an-ode-to-the-13-inch-macbook-pro</guid><pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2017 13:25:00 -0800</pubDate></item><item><title>California Bills to Safeguard Privacy from the Federal Government Advance</title><link>http://brianschrader.com/archive/california-bills-to-safeguard-privacy-from-the-federal-government-advance/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2017/02/california-bills-safeguard-privacy-federal-government-pass-committee"&gt;Rainey Reitman for the EFF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New state bills that would create a database firewall between California and the federal government passed out of their respective Senate committees on Tuesday. Both are headed to the Appropriations Committee and then could soon see votes by the full California Senate. If passed, these critical bills would help prevent Muslim registries and mass deportations in California and would send a strong message to the Trump administration that Californians will resist his attacks on digital liberty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is some much needed positive Government-related news. I have no idea how legal it is for California to directly oppose Trump's ideas, but I'm all for them. California is the most powerful state in the U.S. by economy and population; let's see what happens when that power gets put to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know how much control California has over Silicon Valley companies and their databases, but those are arguably the most important stores of personal data in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importantly, these pro-privacy policies will outlast President Trump. Once baked into California law, they&#8217;ll safeguard the over 38 million residents of California for generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the bottom of the EFF blog post there's ways to contact your representatives and tell them you support this measure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2017/02/california-bills-safeguard-privacy-federal-government-pass-committee"&gt;California Bills to Safeguard Privacy from the Federal Government Advance &amp;#8594;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>eff</category><category> trump</category><category> digital rights</category><category> nobannowall</category><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/california-bills-to-safeguard-privacy-from-the-federal-government-advance</guid><pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2017 14:07:00 -0800</pubDate></item><item><title>The Internet Won't Forget Climate Change</title><link>http://brianschrader.com/archive/the-internet-wont-forget-climate-change/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A lot of you might have seen this post on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The tweet about NOAA" src="//aftp-cmdl-noaa-gov.brianschrader.com/theme/tweet.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did, though I didn't put it in with my baby pictures, &lt;a href="//aftp-cmdl-noaa-gov.brianschrader.com"&gt;I put it here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href="//aftp-cmdl-noaa-gov.brianschrader.com"&gt;aftp-cmdl-noaa-gov.brianschrader.com&lt;/a&gt; is a full mirror of the contents of that FTP site. It has all of the CO2 and Aerosol data that NOAA has made available (all the way back to 1976). If you find this data useful, I'd love to hear from you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're looking for other climate change related data sets, &lt;a href="//climate.daknob.net"&gt;The Climate Mirror Project&lt;/a&gt; has lots of mirrors of NASA, NOAA, and other organizations. We will not allow this data to be forgotten. Climate change is real, it's a problem, and it's getting worse. &lt;a href="//www.nytimes.com/2017/01/20/us/politics/trump-white-house-website.html?_r=0"&gt;Ignoring it cannot be the solution&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Internet should not forget; we can't let it forget something this important.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>politics</category><category> trump</category><category> open data</category><category> climate change</category><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/the-internet-wont-forget-climate-change</guid><pubDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2017 17:09:00 -0800</pubDate></item></channel></rss>