<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" version="2.0"><channel><title>BiteofanApple</title><link>http://brianschrader.com</link><description>Thoughts, and ramblings about technology, programming, history,
 and whatever else I'm interested in.</description><language>en-US</language><image><url>https://www.gravatar.com/avatar/11b074a636e00292c98e3e60f7e16595</url><title>Brian Schrader</title><link>http://brianschrader.com</link></image><lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 00:29:42 +0000</lastBuildDate><generator>sonicrocketman-feed-generator/v2.0</generator><atom:link href="https://brianschrader.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><category>programming</category><category>history</category><category>science</category><category>personal</category><category>technology</category><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/on-the-lies-depression-tells</guid><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 03:10:00 -0800</pubDate><category>personal</category><category>human condition</category><category>writing</category><category>essay</category><title>On the Lies Depression Tells</title><link>https://brianschrader.com/archive/on-the-lies-depression-tells/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>I'm no stranger to depressive episodes, though thankfully mine are sparse and usually brief: sometimes a day or two, though on rare occasions perhaps a week or more. I'm thankful mine have never progressed into anything serious. That said, I'd like to discuss something that's become somewhat of a theme in my conversations lately about depression, and something I hope you, the reader, might find useful when combatting this Great and Terrible Beast yourself.</p>
<p>To begin, I'd like to draw a distinction between depression and melancholy. There's a beauty to melancholy<sup>1</sup> that there simply isn't with depression. One begets yearning, the other smothers everything in its path. I love melancholy, I really do, enough that sometimes I work to keep it going a little longer. Melancholy is a mourning wistfulness, the loss of something dearly loved, a cousin of grief and dour predilections.</p>
<p>Depression is a plastic bag, thrown over your head to choke off every breath of air until you succumb to its will. It's insidious, and <em>it lies to you</em>.</p>
<h2>The Venomous Snake</h2>
<p>Depression, however brief or fleeting, is the bedfellow of despair. They don't always arrive together, but they are never long apart. Both weave a web of thought that strangles fragile hope and sets to bury will and want beneath the mountain of excuse.</p>
<div class="image-right" style="width: 100%;">
<img src="/images/blog/depression.jpeg" alt="" style="max-width: unset; width: 100%;">
</div>

<p>Despair works slowly, convincing&mdash;no, <em>proving</em>&mdash;to you that this is how the world is: that it's terrible, that it has always been terrible, and that it will always be terrible. Then Depression swoops in like a hero to stifle that pain with dullness.</p>
<p>Depression and Despair have all the rhetorical skill of Cicero: ethos, pathos, and lagos enough to destroy whatever justification you can weakly muster to your own defense. That's what makes Depression and Despair the monsters that they are. They pull the ultimate trick: not only to convince you of their lies, but to convince you that they&mdash;not hope&mdash;hold the truth about the world, that theirs is the only word you can trust, and that no amount of reason, logic, hope, or will can overcome their hold and free you from their grasp. They are fighters, brandishing their weapons of thought that cut you where it hurts the most.</p>
<p>And their trap is nearly perfect. <em>Nearly.</em></p>
<p>In D&amp;D a Fighter is extremely difficult to kill, but a Wizard is invincible if they're properly prepared. No swashbuckling swordsman will ever survive the onslaught of a Wizard's Tower properly fortified. Yet that invincibility requires time to set traps, lay wards, and summon reinforcements.</p>
<h2>Gathering Reinforcements</h2>
<p>I remember a time, about a year ago, when I was in the throws of a particularly bad depressive episode. Every day was the same: I was smothered, unmotivated, sad, dull. I had always felt this way. Weeks had passed since I'd felt anything but soul crushing despair or mind-numbing flatness.</p>
<p>It was right before bed.</p>
<div class="image-right" style="width: 320px;">
<img src="/images/blog/journals.jpg" alt="" style="max-width: unset; width: 100%;">
</div>

<p>Usually I keep a journal, but lately I hadn't kept it up. The depression was overwhelming. I had nothing to write about. Yet, I needed a win, any win. So I summoned the will to write a single sentence. Win complete.  But then Despair told me to flip back a few pages, to read a few old entries, and to confirm my worst fears: that it had always been this way and therefore always would be.</p>
<p>That was its mistake, for in those prior pages lurked a trap that Past Me had unwittingly set. Not a page back, two days prior, it read: "Great day. Really great."</p>
<p>Cracks emerged in the edifice.</p>
<p>I blinked, confused. Had <em>I</em> written this? Was my memory failing me? How could I not remember just two days ago? Suddenly, I did remember. It had been a good day, a great day even! I flipped back further. Another, three days before that: great. Another: two days before that. One a night out, another: a dinner with family, a third: a truly excellent band practice.</p>
<p>How had I forgotten it all?</p>
<p>Stunned, I set the journal down. Memories of seeming-distant days flooded in and I saw the truth. It was as if I'd awoken from a sleep and now could see the nonsense of my dreams. It'd all been a lie, the perfect lie. Perfect because my depression knew exactly how to convince me, knew precisely how to ensure I'd never escape its grasp because it <em>is</em> me. It knows my strengths and weaknesses seemingly better than I do. Yet it had forgotten about my reinforcements&mdash;and nearly made me forget them too. But the cavalry had now been called and my past selves had arrived.</p>
<p>Thus it was the tide of battle turned.</p>
<h2>Evidence of Prior Joy</h2>
<p>I will not tell you that reading those prior journal entries "cured" my depression that day, nor has it ever in the times I've relied upon them since. One cannot vanquish such a beast in one blow. This is not a battle that can be won by your present self alone. However, we are not only our present self. We are the sums of all the people we have ever been and in our darkest hour we can lean on those prior selves for strength. Winning this battle, it takes time. It takes friends and it takes help&mdash;which comes in many forms.</p>
<p>Yet I will tell you that it helps. <strong>Every time, it helps</strong>. On good days and bad, I try to write <em>something</em> in that little book, to gather evidence of prior joy, because that is the best weapon I have found in my battle with this beast. I didn't start journalling years ago with this (or any) goal in mind and never did I imagine that journalling would do anything to help with depression, but it does, precisely because it breaks the illusion that we have perfect memories of anything, even of ourselves.</p>
<p>Such a thought is powerful, but even those are brittle in Depression's grasp. Nothing you say or do in that moment will do you any good, yet writing allows us to bring forth our past selves, through the Mists of Time, and let them speak, not in the words we imagine they had spoke, but in the words they wrote for themselves.</p>
<div class="footnote">
<sup>1</sup> The original quote I wanted to attribute here is from an old episode of The Ezra Klein Show (est. circa 2019) but I can't find the episode transcript to confirm this.
</div>]]></description></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/the-long-view-of-history</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 19:20:00 -0800</pubDate><category>history</category><category>writing</category><category>politics</category><category>essay</category><title>The Long View of History</title><link>https://brianschrader.com/archive/the-long-view-of-history/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>History as a subject is often viewed by students and the public at large as a domain without a use, a pedantic study of dates and names with some vague mission to remember the past&mdash;a memorial to ages past but neither a forward-looking or useful endeavor. The study of history produces teachers of history and nothing more. And while the study of history does not produce new widgets or novel computer advances, and nor does it deepen our understanding of materials science or physics.</p>
<p>The humanities, in which history and studies of language and culture are a part, are not there to improve our understanding of nature or develop technology, they exist to improve the minds (both cultural and individual) of the people we are.</p>
<p>History doesn't improve our world, it improves <em>us</em>. It gives us context for the world we live in and it helps us understand the reason why things are as they are and learn from the people before us.</p>
<h2>History as Context</h2>
<p>Imagine waking up every day with no memory of the day before, no idea who owned the house you slept in, no idea what country you're in, and no idea why everyone around you speaks the languages they do.</p>
<div class="image-right" style="max-width: 300px;">
<img style="max-width: unset; width: 100%;" alt="" src="/images/blog/hart-bolton-american-history-maps-58c658-1024.jpg">
<center><small>Photo Credit: <a href="https://www.loc.gov/resource/g3701s.cw0004000/">Library of Congress</a></small></center>
</div>

<p>Living in such a world would be disorienting, confusing, non-sensical. Yet this is the world without history. <strong>The world without history just is</strong>. It isn't a work in progress, but a finished piece&mdash;one that lives and dies with you&mdash;and has no meaning beyond the present moment.</p>
<p>History doesn't let us predict the future, but it can be an enormous help in explaining the present. Current events are utterly indecipherable without the context of history and within that context, they feel less and less apart. Indeed our recent past of the Post-War Order is the oddity in history, and a real thing to be cherished and seen as something fleeting, fragile, and truly precious.</p>
<p>Yet without the context of history, we're blind to the reality that we live in a world truly set apart from everything that's come before <em>and</em> one that's deeply connected and familiar to the worlds of the past. That context is important because it gives us the vision to see the world that could be, both the paths of dark and of light that are set before us. It shows us who we are.</p>
<h2>History as Memory</h2>
<p>Living Memory is the collective memory of everyone alive in our society today. It is ever-changing and ever-fleeting. We remember the 2008 Financial Crisis quite well, but our memory of World War 2 is all but gone now. We read about it, sure, but our collective living memory of it has diminished and with that lapsing has gone all the memory of precisely <em>why</em> the world is ordered the way it is. This is not a value judgement, it is a statement of fact.</p>
<div class="image-right" style="max-width: 330px;">
<img style="max-width: unset; width: 100%;" alt="" src="/images/blog/roman-ag.jpg">
<center><small>Photo Credit: <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=1717518">DieBuche, CC BY-SA 3.0,</a></small></center>
</div>

<p>In a couple <a href="/archive/blogging-writing-musing-and-thinking/">recent</a> <a href="/archive/your-brain-is-an-l1-cache/">posts</a>, I describe how I try to use writing by hand as a way to increase my understanding of myself and my own memory. This is a form of personal history, and I find it difficult to express how much doing so has helped me better understand myself and my own thoughts.</p>
<p>This is analogous to our collective history. Though it's important to remember that history is not the act of writing, but the act of looking back and <em>analyzing</em> what was written. We write so that we can remember. We cannot learn from our mistakes if we refuse to write them down, or worse, if we refuse to look back.</p>
<p>The context of history is terrible and it is beautiful. It is the greatest story ever told with myriad heroes and villans, tragedy and triumph, love and grief all endlessly shifting in and out of view. And it was made (and is <em>being made</em>) by people no different than ourselves. Most of them didn't have the luxury to place themselves within the broader historical narrative. We do. Let's not ignore so precious a gift.</p>]]></description></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/blogging-writing-musing-and-thinking</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 18:08:00 -0800</pubDate><category>blogging</category><category>personal</category><category>writing</category><category>thought technology</category><title>Blogging, Writing, Musing, and Thinking</title><link>https://brianschrader.com/archive/blogging-writing-musing-and-thinking/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I stumbled on this quote from a blog post by <a href="https://www.joanwestenberg.com/the-case-for-blogging-in-the-ruins/">JA Westenberg</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Michel de Montaigne arguably invented the essay in the 1570s, sitting in a tower in his French château, writing about whatever interested him: cannibals, thumbs, the education of children, how to talk to people who are dying. He called these writings essais, meaning "attempts" or "tries." The form was explicitly provisional. Montaigne was trying out ideas, seeing where they led, acknowledging uncertainty as a fundamental feature rather than a bug to be eliminated.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It's hard to convey the sense of both profound agreement and giddy joy I had reading that because, not only is the wider post about something I love (i.e. blogging), or because I learned something new about the history of writing (which is always fun), but because that quote describes something that I've been doing myself for the past two years and wanted an excuse to talk about!</p>
<h2>What Writing Is</h2>
<p>There's an old adage that says, "Writing is Thinking" and I've usually interpreted those words to mean that "writing helps you think", which is undoubtably true. However in recent years I've discovered an entirely new form of writing that I've taken to calling: musing, that I think takes this idea a step further, and it's precisely what Westenberg describes Montaigne doing in the 16<sup>th</sup> century.</p>
<div class="image-right" style="width: 330px; padding-right: 0; ">
<img alt="A collection of my notebooks" src="/images/blog/musingbooks.jpg" style="max-width: 100%; padding-right: 0;"/>
<center><small>An example of the notebooks I use.</small></center>
</div>

<p>We have a lot of thoughts throughout the day, and yet we spend so little time indulging these idle curiosities. Writing, especially by hand, can be a great way to explore these ideas and to practice thinking. It's also really fun to do! Over time I started collecting these ideas into notebooks (one of which I almost always carry with me) in order to better organize these inherently random topics into a searchable system. Originally I scribbled on loose leaf pages or random legal pads (as I've mentioned before) and that became unruly very quickly.</p>
<p>Some of these musings are personal topics, most are not. Often they're just the exploration of a question I have. Here's an example:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Businesses keep offices cold because there's research saying that cooler temperatures help people think and stay focused. Given that's true, could the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Little_Ice_Age">Little Ice Age</a> have helped improve human cognition during the 17<sup>th</sup> and 18<sup>th</sup> centuries? If so, what does that mean?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I'm not sure, but it was something I thought about for a while and so I wrote it down. The entire musing, or essay as I guess it should be called, is less than a page, but was engaging and very fun to do. I've written short essays about dozens of topics over the years (including several that have been eventually <a href="/archive/narrative-structure-and-the-principle-of-least-action/">published</a> to <a href="/archive/the-mysterious-potential-of-the-plane/">this</a> <a href="/archive/empirical-partial-derivatives/">blog</a>). It's a fun practice, and I encourage you to try it.</p>
<details>
  <summary>More Musing Ideas</summary>
  <ul>
    <li>Why am I feeling sad lately?</li>
    <li>Why do we see sunsets as beautiful?</li>
    <li>Second-guessing [prior topic]</li>
    <li>What function does the press fulfill in society?
        <ul>
            <li>Why is that valuable?</li>
            <li>How could that value be measured?</li>
        </ul>
    </li>
    <li>What is the single, smallest change I could make to the U.S. constitution to have the biggest impact on the problems I see?</li>
    <li>
        Do stories follow mathematical laws?
        <ul>
            <li>What would that mean for us?</li>
            <li>How could such a thing be measured?</li>
            <li>How come we seem to intuit these laws?</li>
        </ul>
    </li>
    <li>What is math?</li>
    <li>Is [current stress point] a long-term problem or a temporary one?</li>
    <li>What is the cognitive purpose of stereotypes?</li>
    <li>What would it feel like to live 10,000 years ago?</li>
    <li>Let's try to comprehend the fullness of human history!</li>
    <li>I had an idea for a cool&mdash;but probably useless&mdash;invention!</li>
  </ul>
</details>

<p>Explore your ideas honestly. Don't fear where your mind goes or the questions it will ask. These are personal, honest thoughts not social media posts. Writing like this is inherently introspective, it's a way to give your mind the space to awe and wonder</p>
<h2>What Thinking Is</h2>
<p>We often believe that thinking is a process which takes place entirely in the mind, but it's a process that is heavily influenced by the particulars of the body. Try thinking through a problem in a hot and smelly room or on a walk with a rock in your shoe.</p>
<p><img class="image-right" alt="One of my notebooks" src="/images/blog/notes.jpg" style="width: 330px; padding-right: 0;"/></p>
<p>However, the body can do more than hinder the thought process, it can catalyze it! This is what writing can be, a way to think through problems using your entire body.</p>
<p>Occasionally, I've sat down to write but without any particular topic in mind. So, I open my notebook and just start writing. Tons of my essays begin with something like, "I'm not sure what I'm thinking right now and I don't know what to write." From there, I let my thoughts move and course as they will and I just write down what comes to mind, stopping and starting as my thoughts shift and change and eventually I will find that something has come out of it. I might work through a tension or stress point, I could come to realize or discover something about a problem, or I could just get a few lackluster thoughts on a page. Not all thinking is productive but the mind is a muscle and it needs to be exercised to function properly. Sometimes just doing the workout is enough.</p>
<h2>Thinking as a Skill</h2>
<p>We usually think of cleverness or intelligence as an innate trait people have, and while that is certainly true in some regards, intelligence and wisdom are just as much a function of practice as of talent. To get good at solving puzzles, you have to practice solving puzzles. The mind is no different than a muscle in that regard. Thinking aloud on the page is one way to record and analyze your thought process and to practice the art of thinking itself.</p>
<p>As another example, I often revisit my prior writings and find many to be overly simplistic, uninspired, or just plain wrong. But that's good! It means I've learned something in the intervening time! In software there's an addage:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If you come back to old code and see nothing wrong with it, then you haven't learned anything since.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>You are not a finished product, you're a process&mdash;always in motion&mdash;that evolves and changes over time. Your thinking can improve with practice as much as it can atrophy from inattention.</p>
<p>Think about thinking, write those thoughts down, then perhaps publish a few on a blog that you own. It's fun, and it can do wonders for the mind.</p>]]></description></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/maintaining-a-music-library-ten-years-on</guid><pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 21:11:00 -0800</pubDate><category>music</category><category>software</category><title>Maintaining a Music Library, Ten Years On</title><link>https://brianschrader.com/archive/maintaining-a-music-library-ten-years-on/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>It took me by surprise to learn that <a href="/archive/why-im-switching-back-to-itunes/">this post</a> was now a decade old:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Last week I decided to leave Spotify. I've been using the service for almost 2 years now, and overall I've really liked it... It's hard to explain why [I'm leaving], but I guess I feel apprehensive about Spotify being in control of how and where I listen to music in ways I haven't been before.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I remember the inciting incident so viscerally. I wanted to AirPlay a song to my TV, but that device wasn't "approved by Spotify". It's an MP3 and I couldn't jam out to it because of the policies of some company. I was so angry, so I left. Without a viable alternative, I started buying albums in the iTunes Store like it was 2007 all over again.</p>
<p>It's been ten years now, and I do not regret that choice for a minute.</p>
<h2>Buying Music in 2025</h2>
<p>There is a distinct freedom that comes with owning your own music library. The knowledge that your music isn't going to go away on you someday when you stop paying for access is nice, but even better is the feeling that you're free from the capricious whims of any corporate policy change. If Apple, or whomever, decides to be a jerk, you can take your ball and go home. Your library is yours and can be ported easily to any other app or service you want.</p>
<div class="image-center"><img src="/images/blog/music-2025.webp" alt="A screenshot of my music library as of three months ago." style="max-width: 100%;"><small><center>So much good music. So many local bands.</center></small></div>

<p>Of course there's the rather sizable downside to all of this, which is that music today is largely dominated by platforms like Spotify, etc.. When you buy music in 2025, you're going against the grain. Apple Music has seemingly forgot that people have personal libraries and links exclusively to Apple Music when it is searching for tracks and the iTunes Store is getting quite long in the teeth. Recently, albums have started appearing twice in my library at purchase-time and that mess has to be manually cleaned up.</p>
<p>Still, <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/108935">iTunes Match</a> continues on and so my laptop and my phone continue to be in sync for only $24/yr. If this ever went away, I could always sync manually&mdash;but in reality I'd probably just switch to using Plex for music.</p>
<p>Buying your music is certainly a dying art in 2025, but for now at least, the apps and stores still exist and, largely, work just fine.</p>
<p>Oh, and nobody tell Apple that iTunes Match hasn't been adjusted for inflation, like ever.</p>
<h2>Unspoken Advantages (and a few Disadvantages)</h2>
<p>When I started curating my music again in 2015, I had a few random singles (from those old Starbucks song cards) and a few random anime soundtrack albums I'd gotten from <em>somewhere</em>, back in the day. But, since my musical tastes had changed drastically, I was basically starting from scratch. For the same price as Spotify, I was able to get one album per month until I built up a sizable library&mdash;then my investment started to pay off. I'd go months without buying an album, and I had the freedom to play them anywhere. It was glorious.</p>
<div class="image-center" style="width: 100%; padding: 0; border: 0;"><img src="/images/blog/header.webp" alt="A picture of my record player and my record collection." style="max-width: 100%; padding: 0; border: 0;"></div>

<p>It was around 2017 that I started getting into listening to albums as standalone works, rather than listening to custom playlists of singles. From there it was a straight shot into the world of collecting vinyl records, a hobby I've really grown to love. Buying and listening to whole albums also really put me in tune with the entire feeling of a band. Sure, not all of the songs on an album are bangers, but as <a href="https://colinmeloy.substack.com/p/kill-your-shuffle-button">Colin Meloy of the Decemberists put it</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>[For me, an] album was not just an analog to a short story collection, it was sometimes a novel — each song a different chapter, a different panel in the quilt.</p>
<p>I took artists at their word; the order of an album was as intentional as the lyrics inside the songs. A thread was there to follow; clues to unlock. Even if there was no literal connection between the songs, there was a pattern and a rhythm to the thing.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It's one, long song. That realization changed how I conceive of recorded music.</p>
<p>The main advantages, beyond the freedom I've already mentioned are primarily for people who are really into music and the music ecosystem. Buying music continues to be the best way for artists to make money off of their art. Artists continue to receive 70% of an album's sale price on iTunes compared with the $0.005/stream rate that Spotify charges. As well, maintaining your own music library is the easiest way (even today) to follow indie or local bands who may not have fronted the costs to put themselves on the big platforms.</p>
<p>Buy music on Bandcamp or download it from Soundcloud, stick it in the Music app, and you're off! No switching between a hundred apps, no platform lock in. Just music. It also helps immensely when you're recording your own music (as I do, frequently <a href="https://thefourthsection.com">for my band</a>).</p>
<p>That said, there are some distinct disadvantages to buying music. You miss out on the recommendation features and smart playlists (Genius does still exist but it does and has always sucked). Also, it's basically impossible to share playlists with others or import them for your own use.</p>
<p>You can still burn a CD though, if that's your thing.</p>
<h2>Some Other Musical Thoughts</h2>
<div class="image-container" style="padding-right:0;"><img class="image-right" src="/images/blog/triode.webp" alt="" style="width: 325px; padding:0; margin:0;"></div>

<p>Recently I've gotten back into listening to internet radio. I go in an out with this particular interest, but one thing that's made this particular venture back into the depths much more enjoyable is the app <a href="https://blog.iconfactory.com/2023/09/triode-2-improvements-everywhere/">Triode by Iconfactory</a>. Music.app retains its predecessor iTunes' ability to stream internet radio (as well as burn the aforementioned CDs) but the integration was always half-assed. Triode is just so much better.</p>
<p>Even now, in 2025, I can't see myself switching away from this world any time soon. Buying music is a pain and it's a fading feature, but it's still the best way to actually own and control the music you listen to, and it's the best way to support the artists you love.</p>
<p>Like so many technologies of the early web that we've now nearly lost or forgotten, it's flaws are real. Like RSS and Podcasting, it takes a long time to curate and gather the blogs, shows, and music you want to enjoy and there's a lot of dependence on informal recommendation networks like those from friends or word-of-mouth via the messy world of meatspace (remember that term?). It's a very human, not algorithmic world, and I love it.</p>]]></description></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/empirical-partial-derivatives</guid><pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 17:51:00 -0800</pubDate><category>mathematics</category><category>science</category><category>philosophy</category><category>essay</category><title>Empirical Partial Derivatives</title><link>https://brianschrader.com/archive/empirical-partial-derivatives/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Mathematics and Science are inextricably linked. As the renowned twentieth-century physicist Eugene Wigner wrote, mathematics is "unreasonably successful" in the natural sciences. By this he meant that it seems our entire world is seemingly beholden to the workings of mathematical laws.</p>
<p>Our most fundamental theories are complex systems of dense mathematical formulations that predict the behavior of the world around us so precisely that we’re able to peer into the earliest moments, right after the Big Bang itself and understand the workings of even the most extreme bending of space and time around black holes. Students of physics and the related sciences study these formulations and the mathematics they rely on for years, relentlessly working to gain mastery—and if they’re lucky—some intuition for the behaviors of complex, dynamical systems.</p>
<p>Yet, perhaps this relationship between math and science goes even deeper. Perhaps modern science and the scientific method itself do more than rely on mathematics. Perhaps—in no metaphorical sense—they are mathematics made manifest.</p>
<h2>The Magic of Curves on the Plane</h2>
<p>When Isaac Newton discovered Calculus alongside Gottfried Leibniz in the late seventeenth century, they arguably ushered in the modern world. However on a technical level, what the study of calculus enabled was the ability for mathematics, as a discipline, to rigorously study change. Without wishing to dig up uncomfortable memories of math class, I will attempt to summarize in one sentence the purpose of the entire field of differential calculus. Simply put, rather than like the operations of arithmetic that describe what happens to a quantity when one combines or dissects it, a new kind of operation—the derivative—enables mathematicians to study how, and how quickly, a quantity changes over time (like the velocity of a ball rolling down a slope) or over space (like how weather patterns vary by region).</p>
<p><img class="image-center" style="width: 100%; max-width:unset;" src="/images/blog/partial-derivative-graph-top.jpg" alt="Partial Derivatives on a plot" />
<small><center>A curve on the plane.</center></small></p>
<p>Now, even that one sentence was a lot to take in, so if you take nothing else from this section, let it be this: a derivative measures the rate of change.
Often times however, a system is complex and can change in multiple ways at once. Consider a system far more complex than a ball on a hill: the human body.
No matter how much we as a society might wish it to be true, healthy living is not a simple function of one variable. There are lots of factors that can affect a person’s health and each does so in a different way. Exercise is good for you, but so is maintaining a good diet and not smoking. A myriad of factors, both known and unknown, affect overall health—including sheer dumb luck. But how are we to make sense of this tangled knot of cause and effect?</p>
<p>Enter, the modern scientific method and the randomized controlled clinical trial.</p>
<h2>Empirical Meets Theoretical</h2>
<p>Researchers looking to tease apart the effects of a new diet plan on patient’s overall health could choose to assemble a group of people who all share the same socioeconomic background, are around the same age, the same height and weight, and who exercise around the same amount of time every week. Since these factors are held in common, they can be assumed to affect all of the participants equally and thus factors like height, weight, wealth, and exercise are held constant or controlled for during the time of the experiment. The researchers will then divide the group in two, giving one half the novel diet plan and the other a more traditional and well researched plan to act as a control. Thus, the only factor which is free to vary between the groups, their diet, is finally made available to study.</p>
<p>In effect, this method allows the researchers to—in principle—assume all other factors remain constant and our complex system of multiple variables has been simplified into a simple function of one. Measuring the ensuing rate of change is then an empirical derivative, allowing us to ascertain the nature of the change we’ve just caused.</p>
<p><img class="image-center" style="width: 100%; max-width:unset;" src="/images/blog/partial-derivative-graph-bottom.jpg" alt="Partial Derivatives on a plot" />
<small><center>The true underlying surface.</center></small></p>
<p>This example is more than analogous to mathematics. Advanced students of mathematics study increasingly complex systems and to do so must learn to take something called a partial derivative—which sadly is not any simpler, despite how it may sound. These systems combine several interdependent variables and thus our math students employ the same process as our researchers above.</p>
<p>To take a partial derivative, one must arrange the given system of equations in such a way as to tease apart the influence of each variable and then assume that each can be held constant at the point under consideration with respect to the variable in question. Using different tools the mathematician performs the exact same process as our heath researchers. Where mathematicians deal with systems of abstract equations, our public health scientists do the same with the messy particulars of real life.</p>
<p>None of this is to suggest that economists, public health researchers, and other participants in the empirical sciences do not also use the mathematical techniques of calculus and derivatives in conjunction with their work—of course they do, and in spades. Instead, the point here is to examine how the theoretical methods of advanced math and the practical techniques of scientists today are both really one and the same. The technique of performing a randomized clinical trial works precisely because it is fundamentally an implementation of mathematical theory, a real-world implementation of the work of mathematics. Randomized controlled clinical trial are the act of taking a partial derivative in tangible form and in that way they are the physical incantation of those same discoveries made by Newton and Leibniz all those centuries ago.</p>]]></description></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/chemical-telescopes-and-the-process-of-science</guid><pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 17:04:00 -0800</pubDate><category>science</category><category>history</category><category>technology</category><category>essay</category><title>Chemical Telescopes and the Process of Science</title><link>https://brianschrader.com/archive/chemical-telescopes-and-the-process-of-science/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>In 1619, Daniel Sennert crouched over a low furnace in his cloistered laboratory at the University of Wittenberg. The air was still and stifling. Though the room was packed, no one said a word. Instead, the several dozen learned men who had crammed themselves into the small space stared at a little white crucible as Sennert removed it from the flames. He tipped out the contents and a delicate stream of molten silver ran from the crucible to collect in an earthenware bowl.</p>
<p>Gasps filled the air. Such a thing wasn't supposed to be possible. Chills ran down the spine of every man in that room, even Sennert himself. For he knew, in that moment, the world had changed forever.<sup>1</sup></p>
<h2>The State of Sennert's Science</h2>
<div class="image-container">
<img alt="Sennerts procedure" src="/images/blog/sennert-hypomnemata.jpg" style="max-width: 100%; width:250px;" class="image-right" />
<small><center>Photo credit: Google Books</center></small>
</div>

<p>In the days before Newton, Boyle, Kepler, and others remade the process of scientific inquiry, humanity's understanding of nature and our scientific methods were markedly different. The writings of Aristotle formed the foundations of natural knowledge and the workings of matter were explained by the qualities imparted by abstract Forms, rather than the formulation and arrangement of physical atoms.</p>
<p>From our vantage now, it might seem strange, but the Aristotelean scholars of the time were quite comfortable with their theory's ability to explain the natural world. While their understanding of nature was changing over time (as does ours), it had stood for centuries and they had little empirical evidence that anything was terribly awry.</p>
<p>That is, until the discovery of the mineral acids.</p>
<p>Nitric, hydrochloric, and sulfuric acid were discovered gradually during the middle ages with the first (known as aqua fortis) discovered around 1300 C.E.</p>
<p>Before the use and widespread adoption of the mineral acids in scientific inquiry, it was understood that all materials underwent the same general process: what Aristotle called Corruption and Generation.</p>
<p>Broadly speaking, nature itself generated all primary materials from the four Aristotelean Elements (sometimes five) and then either Nature (or God) imparted that matter with Forms, which determined the perceivable qualities of the matter. Trees were generated (grew) from the earth, then died or were cut down in the process of corruption that resulted in wood, corrupted further to rot and earth, or ash and smoke (depending on the method). The specifics aren't important here. What is important is that Scholastics understood this to be a one-way process. Nature could (re)generate matter from the elements, but after that it was all downhill. Matter underwent corruption after corruption until finally resulting in the four base elements where nature could begin her (re)generation process anew. Nothing humans could do would change that.
As Aristotle said, water, once added to wine, cannot be removed again without destroying the wine.<sup>1</sup></p>
<h2>Then, Everything Changed</h2>
<p>The mineral acids had been used for centuries in various places, but rarely entered the domain of philosophical debate because of a distinctly medieval distain for "practicals" in the development of physical theory. This isn't so much a distaste for experimentation, as is often claimed, but a dislike of certain professions (like that of the tanners or chymists) who followed recipes instead of pursuing a connection to more philosophical ideas. Chymists, for example, were not thought of as practicing rigorous academic study. Their work wasn't connected to any pedigreed Aristotelean foundation, and so they were mere "empirics". Their study was without academic merit.</p>
<div class="image-container">
<img alt="Sennerts procedure" src="/images/blog/sennert-proceduere-desk.jpg" class="image-center" />
</div>

<p>However in 1619, Daniel Sennert, a professor of medicine and an unusually practiced chymist, discovered a curious phenomenon. Sennert was investigating whether dissolving silver in aqua fortis resulted in a truly homogenous mixture (what Scholastics called a mixt). A true mixt would mean that the silver was irrecoverable because a genuine corruption had taken place.</p>
<p>When Sennert pours his liquid through a fine filter paper, he sees no particulates of silver— evidence of a true mixt.</p>
<p>He then adds salt of tartar (potassium carbonate) to his mixture and a white precipitate emerges. He filters and washes this new material and then puts it in a crucible and heats it. Eventually, what emerges is pure, molten silver. Sennert has performed a genuine corruption and then retrieved his starting materials, something which should not have been possible.</p>
<p>Sennert's experiment was notable for two reasons. First, the development of "corpuscular" or what we could call "atomic" theory is notable because it was considered to go against the commonly understood teachings of Aristotle and second because, as William Newman wrote:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In doing [this experiment], [Sennert] had simultaneously shown the inadequacy
of the current scholastic theories of mixture while also providing a convincing demonstration of the reality of semipermanent atoms that experience no substantial modification.<sup>2</sup></p>
</blockquote>
<p>While Sennert himself was able to shoehorn enough traditional theory into the Scholastic framework to explain his results, this same experiment would later be used by Robert Boyle in his book The Skeptical Chymist to attack the foundations of Aristotelean matter theory and help to begin the reformation of chemical science into what we know today.</p>
<h2>Chemical Telescopes Today</h2>
<p>The story of Daniel Sennert is the story of science. Ages had come and gone where Aristotle's theory (with numerous additions and changes) had come to dominate Europe’s intellectual understanding of the world. The theory explained much about the world and several tweaks, additions, and modifications existed to fill the gaps where the base theory fell short.</p>
<p>It wasn't until a new technology came along, a new method of looking at the world and investigating its workings, that the old theories began to crumble. Like Galileo and his astronomical telescope, the mineral acids were a chemical telescope that allowed European scholars to probe nature in new ways and find new evidence that didn't fit their prior understanding. Then they had to come up with new theories to explain it all.</p>
<p>Today we may be in a somewhat analogous place, albeit with far better theories. We can explain nearly every classical physical phenomenon we encounter and we have supremely accurate theories for the behavior of even the most minute particles in all the universe. However there are still many gaps, places where our theories break down or contradict each other and can therefore have no explanatory power.</p>
<p>We've tried to solve this problem with additional theory development, however so long as contradictory experimental evidence is scant we will find ourselves akin to the scholastics of Sennert's time: philosophizing and debating increasingly complex theories that can be tuned any number of ways. The unobservable dimensions, fields, or forces of today are more akin to the abstract Forms of Scholastic thought than we may like to admit.</p>
<h2>The Pendulum Swings</h2>
<p>To paraphrase <a href="https://youtu.be/btzE11jNbj4?si=53yG_wEkLPfuaw3P&amp;t=109">Dr. Asaf Karagila</a>, science is primarily a social activity done by scientists.4 And that social activity has, for lack of a better term, fads. In the long course of science, there have been numerous swings back and forth between a focus on experimentalism and theory development. Theory development has seemingly always held the more prestigious position in the sciences, but it's experimentation that truly drives progress.</p>
<p>It was the failure of the Michelson–Morley experiment that inspired Lorentz and Einstein to remake relativity. It was the failure of classical theory to explain black-body spectra that inspired Max Plank to discover the foundations of quantum theory. And it was the failure of Aristotle's Generation and Corruption to explain Sennert's recovery of silver that helped Sennert and later Boyle and Lavoisier to reform chymistry into modern Chemistry. In each of these cases it was the discovery of contradictory, not complementary, evidence that spurred the greatest periods of theory development.</p>
<p>From all of this—astronomical or chemical telescopes alike—it seems that the wise words of History tell us that when our science gets stuck, it's best to look away from the blackboard and instead ask the Universe some hard questions.</p>
<div class="footnote">
<sup>1</sup> This story is a fictionalization based on real events.<br/>
<sup>2</sup> De generatione et corruptione I
10 328a28–31.<br />
<sup>3</sup> Atoms and Alchemy, William Newman. p123.
</div>]]></description></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/pine-blog-deprecation</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 23:36:00 -0800</pubDate><category>pine.blog</category><category>programming</category><category>meta</category><title>So Long Pine.blog</title><link>https://brianschrader.com/archive/pine-blog-deprecation/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>This post has been a long time coming, but it's finally here now.</p>
<h2>Where did Pine.blog Go?</h2>
<p>Pine.blog has been officially deprecated and deactivated. If you have any questions, comments, or concerns about this deprecation please send an email to <a href="mailto://support@skyrocket.software">support@skyrocket.software</a>.</p>
<h2>Can I Get My Data?</h2>
<p>I believe that all active users were given appropriate notice and time to remove their data, but if you feel the need to contact me about your data (i.e. your feed subscriptions) please get in touch.</p>
<h2>It's Been Fun</h2>
<p>Pine.blog was developed in 2017 as a side project and continued to receive regular updates and even a native app (with a planned macOS app) in 2019. However, over time the situation with Pine.blog never improved to the point of achieving profitability or sustainability with its increasingly complex development. As well, over time my desire to build/maintain and the outlook for social media apps in general diminished and I didn't feel the fire burning in my heart to work on it any longer.</p>
<p>The app had at one point a decent userbase, and one that, if the fire still burned bright, perhaps I would have continued to develop for, however that was not the case.</p>
<p>I met a number of amazing people building this app and learned a ton about how the open web works both technically and socially.</p>
<p>So long Pine.blog, it was fun while it lasted.</p>]]></description></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/spoken-audio-from-automator--netnewswire</guid><pubDate>Sat, 13 Sep 2025 01:33:00 -0800</pubDate><category>programming</category><category>fun</category><title>Spoken Audio from Automator &amp; NetNewsWire</title><link>https://brianschrader.com/archive/spoken-audio-from-automator--netnewswire/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>For those of you out there who still use RSS, and in particular NetNewsWire, I've put together a workflow in Automator that can take the currently selected article and generate an audio file of the spoken text.</p>
<p>I never will wrap my head around AppleScript's peculiar syntax, but regardless I've made the workflow file available for download below.</p>
<p><img alt="A screenshot of the service in use" src="/images/blog/nnw-automator.png" /></p>
<p>I typically use this with <a href="https://overcast.fm">Overcast</a> which allows me to upload files to listen on the go.</p>
<p>Like most people, I want to read more articles than I actually do and this is little script will hopefully help with that.</p>
<p>It might take a while to complete, based on the length of the article, and it saves the final audio file to your desktop.</p>
<p>(warning you do need FFMpeg installed)</p>
<p><a href="/dropzone/Audio from Article.zip">⬇️ Download Here</a></p>]]></description></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/the-strangely-anthropic-form-of-natural-laws</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 01:34:00 -0800</pubDate><category>essay</category><title>The Strangely Anthropic Form of Natural Laws</title><link>https://brianschrader.com/archive/the-strangely-anthropic-form-of-natural-laws/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>In the proceeding five centuries, humanity has made incredible progress in discovering and understanding natural laws. Starting in the sixteenth century, the Early Modern Period, colloquially known as the Scientific Revolution, catapulted humanity into the modern era. Today our knowledge of nature's inexorable laws extends from the largest possible structures in the Universe to the smallest physical components that construct all of reality.</p>
<p>However, a study of the history of science makes it clear that we did not build up this knowledge from either the top down, or the bottom up. We started in the middle. Presumably, humanity discovered the "simplest" laws first (i.e. we picked the low hanging fruit), but this assumption begs the following question:</p>
<p>If nature's various laws at different scales are built up and atop of the laws at lower scales, why and how is it that nature conspired to the laws found at our human scale the easiest to understand?</p>
<h2>A Strange Nadir of Complexity</h2>
<p>Quantum Field Theory (QFT) predicts the behavior of nature's most fundamental components. Notoriously, the subject is incredibly complex. General Relativity, the modern theory of gravity, goes the other direction. It predicts the behavior of matter at the largest scales. And it too is famously difficult to understand and work with. Both are inventions of the advanced mathematics of the twentieth century and both require nearly a decade of dedicated work to understand and manipulate.</p>
<p>Yet, we can and do teach Newton's Laws to high schoolers.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/blog/newton-principia.jpeg" class="image-center" style="width: 400px;" />
<center><small><caption>Photograph: Cambridge University Library/PA</caption></small></center>
</figure>

<p>Mathematics doesn't work this way. Students start with elementary counting and arithmetic, then study geometry, algebra, and a host of other topics in roughly the same order that we discovered them. Physics too is taught in a historical manner, but there&mdash;because of the unique phenomenon we're discussing&mdash;students must be later told to disregard their previous knowledge when learning new subjects. Mathematics, by contrast, will never instruct students to disregard earlier truths when moving on to more complex ones.<sup>1</sup> Arithmetic is not invalid when learning calculus, in fact the opposite is true. Yet, an intuitive understanding of Newtonian Mechanics is useless and even harmful when discussing General Relativity.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/blog/nadir-complexity.png" class="image-center" style="width: 500px;" alt="A totally not-controversial attempt to plot the complexity of various domains of physical laws"/>
<center><small><caption>A totally not-controversial attempt to plot the complexity of various domains of physical laws</caption></small></center>
</figure>

<p>It's almost as if natural laws have this inherent complexity curve that bends upward toward the ends. If so, then that idea would tend to suggest that we function at the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Copernican_principle">perfect place</a>, where physical laws are at their most powerful (complex enough to allow for complex and emergent phenomena like life) while also being at some nadir in computable complexity.</p>
<p>But why should this be so?</p>
<h2>An Anthropic Viewpoint</h2>
<p>Perhaps, though I see no direct evidence to support this argument, it is the case that the laws of nature simply <em>appear</em> less complex at our familiar human scale because we are the ones formulating the laws. Thus the rules by which we construct these laws are somehow intuitively complementary to our human intuitions about the workings of the Universe at that same scale.</p>
<p>Newton's Laws are convenient for describing earthly motion and humans evolved on earth, hence our mathematics bakes in some of our innate intuition about how the world works.</p>
<p>This explains how, when phenomena are more distant from our day-to-day experience, their physical and mathematical descriptions become increasingly complex and non-sensical.</p>
<p>However, this anthropic approach sheds no light on precisely what sorts of intuitive principles we've baked into our mathematics and, looking at the commonly-used ZFC axioms which underly much of modern mathematics, it's hard to see exactly what "human intuitions" can be found there, at least from my perspective.</p>
<h2>Wondering Aloud</h2>
<p>For now, it remains something of a mystery to me exactly why this phenomenon of the strange dip in complexity exists. I'm sure that I'm not the first to see or wonder about this curious case, but I'm also not sure precisely how to search for or investigate this topic further. If anyone knows more or can recommend a few papers or a book on the subject, please get in touch.</p>
<div class="footnote">
<sup>1</sup> To be complete, Mathematics often instructs students to disregard prior notions when generalizing a given concept, but the earlier notions are never "disproven", instead they are explored in greater nuance.
</div>]]></description></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://brianschrader.com/archive/your-brain-is-an-l1-cache</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 16:30:00 -0800</pubDate><category>philosophy</category><title>Your Brain is an L1 Cache</title><link>https://brianschrader.com/archive/your-brain-is-an-l1-cache/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>These days I think a lot about thinking, and I'm often reminded about something <a href="https://youtu.be/QC-cMv0e3Dc?si=44bldFW7Wjork6QX&amp;t=129">CGP Grey said</a> many years ago:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The single thing that changed me the most was keeping a paper notebook and writing down my thoughts and simply looking back at that notebook on a regular basis... it's so simple but it comes down to <strong>increasing communication between past, present, and future you.</strong> That's what helps you direct change in yourself over time.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This quote has really stuck with me over the years and hopefully I can adequately explain why.</p>
<h2>The Matter of the Mind</h2>
<p>The brain is a miraculous and wondrous thing, but however fantastical its capacity, it has never been possible to keep everything we experience, know, understand, or wish to remember in our heads at once. Hence, we record such things outside of our brains if we wish to someday recall them. We use calendars, notebooks (and books in general), videos, memes, smart phones, sharpie-covered-forearms, and all manner of other non-brain spaces to jot down and persist our ever-fleeting thoughts. The brain's space is very limited, especially given the demands of our modern world, and while it is fast to recall information (usually) it is easily overwhelmed and must depend on more durable forms of memory for concrete details or in-depth analysis.</p>
<p>Sounds a lot like computer memory, doesn't it?</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/blog/storage-vs-speed.jpg" alt="A chart of the reciprocal nature of speed of access versus storage capacity." style="max-width: 100%; width: 100%; border-radius: 3px; padding: 0; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;">
<small><center>Image credit: mine</center></small>
</figure>

<p>Well, the analogy goes deeper! Indeed, if one needs to add more system memory to a computer, we add more RAM: a slower, yet more expansive pool of memory. When this overflows, we can swap to disk or write files which we later come back to. The same is true&mdash;almost literally and by design&mdash;in ourselves.</p>
<h2>Where the Mind Resides</h2>
<p>The question of <q>where <em>precisely</em> does our mind reside?</q> has dogged humanity for millenia, but if one takes the idea that the mind is able to be comprised of things outside the body then it only makes sense that our smartphones, notebooks, and other physical media we interact with <em>are</em> a core part of our own minds. These media are slower to recall information from and require constant upkeep to avoid losing, degrading, or fragmenting&mdash;but so do all forms of computer memory and storage. Notebooks must be constantly upkept to stay relevant, digital files backed up and properly organized, and books must be catalogued and their core tenants bookmarked, dog-earred, or otherwise recorded for later reference.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/blog/cluttered-desk.jpg" alt="A picture of my cluttered desk." style="max-width: 100%; width: 100%; border-radius: 3px; padding: 0; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;">
<small><center>No, my desk isn't normally this cluttered.</center></small>
</figure>

<p>Thinking of the world in this way, even other people become a form of our own minds: we share information with others who later remind us of what we said. It's an incredibly lossy and error-prone medium, but it is an important one and perhaps the oldest form we know.</p>
<p>When thinking of the world in this way, the idea that one <em>wouldn't</em> want to keep notes, organize files, record memories, take pictures, and scrawl every meaningful thought on whatever was around to record it seems strange to me. By  choosing not to record one's thoughts, one chooses to succumb to a natural form of memory loss: the default form of human dementia.</p>
<p>Obviously not everything is important or worth recording and one cannot always know in advance what will turn out to be important later, but if it feels important or insightful, write it down. Then, critically, come back to it later. That last step is important, because information lost or unread is just a scribble of ink on the pressed pulp of trees.</p>]]></description></item></channel></rss>